<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: computer science | amber tunnell]]></title>
  <link href="http://ambertunnell.github.io/blog/categories/computer-science/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://ambertunnell.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-07T12:12:18-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://ambertunnell.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Amber Tunnell]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[amber.tunnell@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Insertion Sort in Ruby]]></title>
    <link href="http://ambertunnell.github.io/blog/2014/08/23/insertion-sort-in-ruby/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-23T16:01:26-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ambertunnell.github.io/blog/2014/08/23/insertion-sort-in-ruby</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Insertion sort is another simple sorting algorithm. It creates a new array and iterates up the current array, placing the current element into the correct place in the new sorted array.</p>

<ol>
  <li>First, take the first element of the unsorted array out of the array and put it into an empty new array.</li> 
  <li>Take the next element out of the unsorted array and place it into the new array. If it is smaller than the first element in the new array, swap them. If not, leave it at the end.
  <li>Take the next element out of the array and put it at the end of the new array. If it is larger than the previous end element, leave it. If not, iterate through the array until you find its correct position and insert it there.
  <li>Continue this process until your original array is empty and you have a new completely sorted array.</li>
</ol>




<!-- more -->


<p style="text-align:center;"> <img src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/0/0f/Insertion-sort-example-300px.gif" title="Insertion Sort" alt="insertion sort video" /></p>

<p>While more efficent than Bubble Sort, Insertion Sort still has the same average and worse case time complexity of O(n<sup>2</sup>). Like Bubble Sort, it is very inefficient for large data sets, but rather efficient for small data sets or data sets already mostly sorted (the best case time complexity is O(n)).</p>

<p>Implementation of Insertion Sort in Ruby.</p>

<p>```ruby insertion sort
class InsertionSort</p>

<p>  def initialize(array)</p>

<pre><code>@array = array
@sorted_array = []
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def sort</p>

<pre><code>j = 0
while @array.length &gt; 0
  @sorted_array &lt;&lt; @array.shift
  if @sorted_array.length &gt; 1 &amp;&amp; @sorted_array[j-1] &gt; @sorted_array[j]
    @sorted_array.each.with_index do |n, i|
      if @sorted_array[i] &gt; @sorted_array[-1]
        @sorted_array[i], @sorted_array[-1] = @sorted_array[-1], @sorted_array[i]
      end
      if (@sorted_array[i] &lt;  @sorted_array[-1]) &amp;&amp; (@sorted_array[i+1] &gt; @sorted_array[-1])
        @sorted_array.insert(i+1, @sorted_array[-1])
        @sorted_array.slice!(-1)
      end
    end 
  end 
  j+=1
end
@sorted_array
</code></pre>

<p>  end
end</p>

<p>print InsertionSort.new([4,1,6,3,5,2]).sort #=> [1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6]
```</p>

<p><em>This is the second post of a series of posts on various sorting algorithms. See the first here: <a href="http://ambertunnell.github.io/blog/2014/08/20/bubble-sort-in-ruby/">Bubble Sort</a></em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Bubble Sort in Ruby]]></title>
    <link href="http://ambertunnell.github.io/blog/2014/08/20/bubble-sort-in-ruby/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-20T21:37:50-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://ambertunnell.github.io/blog/2014/08/20/bubble-sort-in-ruby</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Sorting algorithms are rarely discussed in Ruby. Most sorting algorithm problems can be solved quite easily by using built-in Ruby methods. That being said, some people feel that it is important to understand the different sorting techniques available in computer science. Along those lines, here&rsquo;s a series of blog posts on sorting algorithms in Ruby!</em></p>

<p>We&rsquo;ll start with Bubble Sort.</p>

<p><strong>Bubble Sort</strong> is a simple sorting algorithm.</p>

<ol>
  <li>You start by comparing the first two items in an array. If the first item is larger than the second, you swap the two items.</li> 
  <li>Then, you compare the second and third items. If the second is larger than the third, you swap them.</li>
  <li>Continue until you reach the end of the array.</li>
  <li>Then, you start from the beginning again and repeat the process until you have one full pass of the array in which you did not swap any items.</li>
  <li>You now have a sorted array!</li>
</ol>




<!-- more -->


<p>The name &lsquo;bubble sort&rsquo; derives from the event of the smaller numbers slowly &lsquo;bubbling&rsquo; to the front of the array through the swapping process.</p>

<p style="text-align:center;"> <img src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/c/c8/Bubble-sort-example-300px.gif" title="Bubble Sort" alt="bubble sort video" /></p>

<p>Here&rsquo;s the bubble sort algorithm implemented in Ruby.</p>

<p>```ruby bubble sort
class BubbleSort</p>

<p>  def initialize(array)</p>

<pre><code>@array = array
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>  def sort</p>

<pre><code>loop do 
  i = 1
  swap_number = 0
 while i &lt; @array.length 
   if @array[i-1] &gt; @array[i]
    @array[i-1], @array[i] = @array[i], @array[i-1] 
    swap_number += 1
   end
   i+=1
 end
  break if swap_number == 0
end 
return @array
</code></pre>

<p>  end</p>

<p>end</p>

<p>print BubbleSort.new([4,1,2,6,3,5]).sort #=> [1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6]
```</p>

<p>One of the biggest problems with using bubble sort is that it isn&rsquo;t practical on large data sets. It is incredibly inefficient with an average and worst-case time complexity of О(n<sup>2</sup>).</p>

<p>In the best-case where the array is already sorted, the time complexity is O(n) because it only has to do one pass of the array, whereas most other algorithms still have to go through all their steps even when given an already-sorted array.</p>

<p>That being said, bubble sort is still a very undesirable and inefficient sorting technique.</p>

<p><em>This is the first post of a series of posts on various sorting algorithms.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
